<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Carl Räfting</title>
 <link href="http://carlrafting.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://carlrafting.com/"/>
 <updated>2013-03-03T01:29:06+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://carlrafting.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Carl Räfting</name>
   <email>carl.rafting@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>autogrow — Less frustrating textareas</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/autogrow-less-frustrating-textareas"/>
   <updated>2012-05-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/autogrow-less-frustrating-textareas</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlrafting.com/designgrid-a-grid-tool-for-fluid-grids&quot;&gt;about one week after i released designGrid&lt;/a&gt;, i published yet another little project that i’ve been working on. This time i’m trying to solve the problem with textareas, or rather the frustration of using them, especially when you’re going to write a lot of text. See textareas are designed to always have a fixed height and when you’re typing a lot it becomes hard to get a coherent sense of what you’ve written. Of course the scrollbar will eventually appear, but instead of it appearing on the text area itself, it will appear on the page, like it should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason i even made this is of course because i needed it myself, and i’ll probably need it in the future as well. I stumbled in to this problem with text areas when i was working on a web app a while ago, and luckily i found out about Neil Jenkins article “Expanding Textareas made elegant” over at A List Apart, which was the solution i was looking for. So i based autogrow on the code from the article, but made it to be more customizable and reusable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interested?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds like something that you could make use of, &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlrafting.com/autogrow/&quot;&gt;head on over to the project&amp;#8217;s home page&lt;/a&gt;, and when you&amp;#8217;re done reading, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carlrafting/autogrow&quot;&gt;download the source code from Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>designGrid — A grid-tool for fluid grids</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/designgrid-a-grid-tool-for-fluid-grids"/>
   <updated>2012-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/designgrid-a-grid-tool-for-fluid-grids</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/10.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last &lt;time datetime=&quot;2012-04-22&quot;&gt;Sunday&lt;/time&gt; i set out to tackle an issue i had. The issue was that i didn’t really know how to design with fluid grids in a good way. Every since i started designing in a responsive manner, i had almost abandoned grids completely, but sometimes there where a need for order but i didn&amp;#8217;t have a tool that could help me out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before i used &lt;a href=&quot;http://hashgrid.com&quot;&gt;#grid&lt;/a&gt;, by the folks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://analog.coop&quot;&gt;Analog&lt;/a&gt;, to make sure my design followed the grid, but then responsive web design and fluid grids came along, and it didn&amp;#8217;t work out anymore. I needed something that was more suitable toward responsive designs. This is my attempt. A first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal was to get something out there as quickly as possible, and worry about optimization and performance later. All in all i spent about a week to get to where i am now, i  designed the grid layout and some basic script functionality the first day. Following days was spent on code for generating a baseline grid and columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Check it out!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;/designGrid/&quot;&gt;check out more about the project and how to set up the grid&lt;/a&gt;, and then &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carlrafting/designGrid&quot;&gt;download the code from Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A note on media-queries and mobile devices</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/media-queries-and-mobile-devices"/>
   <updated>2011-11-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/media-queries-and-mobile-devices</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These days, there is a lot of talk about reponsive design and mobile/content first. While i think we can agree on that these strategies isn&amp;#8217;t entirely bulletproof (yet!), they have a ceratin appeal and can be fairly easy to implement and use today. I do believe that this approach is better than making a mobile version of a website, but that is probably necessary sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon an issue when i was working on a web-application the other day. I had just finished the design in photoshop and then i built the templates in html/css. I should point out that this was the &lt;em&gt;desktop&lt;/em&gt; version of the design. Later on i wanted to make it look good on mobile devices as well, so i set up a media query in the stylesheet to cover the design changes for those kinds of devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue appeared to me at this stage of the process, the mobile devices would need to download the extra set of styles to reset the &lt;em&gt;desktop&lt;/em&gt; styles. This is a bit of an issue, since when we talk about mobile, we asume that the device has significantly less bandwith than a desktop computer. That&amp;#8217;s not necessarily true &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the time but it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be most of the time, if one is on a bus-commute for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mobile-first&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that is where mobile first comes in, the problem however has to do with when one would build templates from a photoshop design that covers the &amp;#8220;desktop&amp;#8221; version. It is a bit hard to develop with the mobile first approach in this case, since the templates has to match the original design as close as possible (That doesn&amp;#8217;t mean it has to be pixel perfect or even look exactly the same in all browsers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So i tought about this some more… And finally i came to the conclusion that the best way for me was to reset the desktop styles on mobile devices (and narrower viewports), since i wanted to keep them separate from each other (easier to maintain). This means however that mobile devices do indeed get a bit heavier stylesheet than what&amp;#8217;s necessary, but on the other hand, there&amp;#8217;s no extra http request needed. This certainly isn&amp;#8217;t the most perfect solution, but at this stage in the development process it was the best way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Responder</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/first-responder"/>
   <updated>2011-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/first-responder</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In his latest blog-post, Rob Weychert writes about how he constructed his first responsive design, which is his own website and blog. He goes into detail about how his grid is constructed and scales to different viewports (or even devices).&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>We, Who Are Web Designers</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/we-who-are-web-designers"/>
   <updated>2011-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/we-who-are-web-designers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jon Tangerine writes about what it means to be a web designer and how sometimes, people will have the wrong idea about what it is you actually do. Every web designer should read this.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New webproject. A quick silly ~1 hour weekend project</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/new-webproject"/>
   <updated>2011-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/new-webproject</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This idea came to me when i thought to myself, what if i could just type one command into the terminal, and the folders and documents i needed where there? I immediately got to work and came up with this, it doesn&amp;#8217;t look much yet but it is indeed handy and i intend to expand it further than this. Say, maybe get a bunch of files from github?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay let&amp;#8217;s not get ahead of ourselves here, time will tell if i&amp;#8217;ll actually add this. Anyway… This isn&amp;#8217;t a groundbreaking new project of mine, it&amp;#8217;s just a result of making reality of an idea i had, and it worked. As simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carlrafting/new_webproj&quot;&gt;Check it out at github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Flat, simple icons for interface design</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/flat-simple-icons-for-interface-design"/>
   <updated>2011-08-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/flat-simple-icons-for-interface-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the hunt for icons for your next design project? Meagan Fisher has, with help from Twitter, compiled a list with nice icons.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Evolution of a Design</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/evolution-design"/>
   <updated>2011-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/evolution-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that makes designing for the web so appealing, is that it&amp;#8217;s either cheap or even free to improve and iterate on a design over time, this is something that doesn&amp;#8217;t work in, for example print (for obvious reasons). Unfortunatly this is something that doesn&amp;#8217;t always happen when web designers work for clients, but on the other hand, changing a design too much would confuse potential customers. So what it comes down to is figuring out how much of the design &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be improved upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, i&amp;#8217;ve done some iterations on an initial design of this site&amp;#8217;s design, which&amp;#8217;ve turned in to what you see now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Initial design concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;media-content&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/9t.png?1310831339&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first design concept i came up with. Initially i was going to use this for tumblr, but soon i turned back to TextPattern. It has no archive or about page and a small amount of visual elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Current design concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;media-content&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/8.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/8t.png?1310831320&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than starting from scratch i added to the already existing design, and you can see that it still shares some basic visual elements as typography and layout. Over time i made the layout responsive, added a navigation and made improvements to the archive page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me this is what makes designing for the web interesting but also challenging and it&amp;#8217;s what sets the web apart from other mediums, the ability to constantly iterate and improve upon certain aspects of a website or applications design. This can be both good or bad , but fortunatley it&amp;#8217;s easier to righten a misstake.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On Tools and Clients</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/tools-and-clients"/>
   <updated>2011-07-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/tools-and-clients</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Noah Stokes touches on a subject that is very common in the web community, the focus on why the tools are so great rather than the focus on solving the clients current issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTML5. CSS3. Responsive Web Design. Sass. Less. Javascript Frameworks. No one cares about this stuff. Let me back up, the people who pay me money to build their sites/apps don’t care about this stuff. Why would they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Responsive Web Design</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/responsive-web-design"/>
   <updated>2011-06-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/responsive-web-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ethan Marcotte&amp;#8217;s long awaited &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design&quot;&gt;book about responsive web design&lt;/a&gt; is finally here. To get a sense of what responsive web design is all about, you should &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alistapart.com/articles/responsive-web-design/&quot;&gt;check out the article&lt;/a&gt; Ethan wrote on the subject over at A List Apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethan describes a bit what the book is a about &lt;a href=&quot;http://unstoppablerobotninja.com/entry/a-book-called-responsive-web-design/&quot;&gt;in a blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s the book about and stuff I guess,” you ask. Well, Responsive Web Design expands on the ideas I articulated in the original article. It’s a crash course in how you can apply fluid grids, flexible images, and media queries to your own work, but let’s face it: design is so much more than those three ingredients. As a result, I’ve tried to share a few stories I’ve picked up from working on real, live responsive projects: the lessons I’ve learned, the questions that have been raised, the hard choices made. The result is a beautifully designed little book (take a bow, Jason) that contains everything you need to start exploring a more flexible, more responsive approach to designing for the web. And at 150 pages, it won’t overstay its welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/beep/status/78069978355597312&quot;&gt;released two days ago&lt;/a&gt; and Roger Johansson has already &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.456bereastreet.com/archive/201106/responsive_web_design_book_review/&quot;&gt;written a review on the book&lt;/a&gt;, and there&amp;#8217;s a portion of chapter 3, called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alistapart.com/articles/fluid-images/&quot;&gt;Fluid Images&lt;/a&gt;, posted at A List Apart as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what Roger has to say about the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking “Ah, yes, this is the right way forward” after reading Jeffrey Zeldman’s article To Hell With Bad Browsers over ten years ago. Reading Responsive Web Design gives me that same feeling of wanting to apply what I’ve just read about right away. It could very well turn out to be a classic comparable to Jeffrey Zeldman’s Designing with Web Standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design&quot;&gt;book is available over at A Book Apart&lt;/a&gt;, $18.00 for the paperback version and $9.00 for the ebook version, there&amp;#8217;s a $23.00 bundle as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Success, and Farming vs. Mining</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/farming-vs-mining"/>
   <updated>2011-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/farming-vs-mining</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wil Shipley talks about the farming vs. mining approach as a metaphor for running a software business, but he also talks a bit about the value of &amp;#8216;having an idea&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;http://blog.wilshipley.com/2011/04/success-and-farming-vs-mining.html&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s upsetting is the number of people who have come to me with the idea of becoming miners: “I know nothing about software, but I can see there’s gold in them thar’ hills, and so I want to start up a company and make my million dollars! I’ve got an idea and everything, just tell me what magic incantation you did to get rich and I’ll be on my way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t work. Your idea sucks. No, I’m not calling you stupid — my idea sucks, too. All ideas suck, because they are just ideas. They’re worth nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My success is because I worked to make the idea real. A lot. All my life. Starting when I was 12, I learned to program, and I’ve programmed every spare moment since. I didn’t become a millionaire until I’d worked at it for eighteen years. There was no genius idea I had. I just kept working, hating what I did before, and working some more to make it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Web Standards Sherpa</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/web-standards-sherpa"/>
   <updated>2011-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/web-standards-sherpa</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An excerpt from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://webstandardssherpa.com/about&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt;, explaining what the goal of the site is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of WebStandardsSherpa.com is to provide web professionals the opportunity to receive feedback, glean advice and learn best practices from experts in the field to help them improve the quality of their own work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web Standards Sherpa is a project from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webstandards.org/&quot;&gt;The Web Standards Project&lt;/a&gt;. Aaron Gustafson explains a bit about the project &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webstandards.org/2011/03/13/the-sherpas-are-here/&quot;&gt;in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web Standards Sherpa came about because we wanted to create a repository of best practices information while, at the same time, providing mentorship opportunities for practicing web professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Cederholm, Founder and Principal of &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplebits.com/&quot;&gt;SimpleBits&lt;/a&gt;, handled the initial design and art direction of the project which he talks about &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplebits.com/notebook/2011/03/14/webstandardssherpa/&quot;&gt;in a blog post on his site&lt;/a&gt;. There are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dribbble.com/shots/130502-Shirley&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://dribbble.com/shots/121853-Pack&quot;&gt;shots&lt;/a&gt; up on &lt;a href=&quot;http://dribbble.com/&quot;&gt;Dribble&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Method &amp; Craft</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/method-craft"/>
   <updated>2011-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/method-craft</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently launched and built by &lt;a href=&quot;http://philcoffman.com/&quot;&gt;Phil Coffman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://noahstokes.com/&quot;&gt;Noah Stokes&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://trentwalton.com/&quot;&gt;Trent Walton&lt;/a&gt;. The about page explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all use the same tools, but we use them differently. We strive to educate you on more efficient, creative, and engaging ways to create your design. This site will not only be valuable to creative veterans, but also educational to those new to the design field. It&amp;#8217;s like looking over the shoulder of your favorite designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using PHP Files For Pages &amp; Article Forms in Textpattern</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/using-php-files-for-pages-article-forms-in-textpattern"/>
   <updated>2010-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/using-php-files-for-pages-article-forms-in-textpattern</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jon Hicks tip on &lt;a href=&quot;http://hicksdesign.co.uk/journal/using-files-for-page-templates-in-textpattern&quot;&gt;Using files for page templates in Textpattern&lt;/a&gt;, it is now a lot easier to work even more rapidly. I&amp;#8217;d like to share some tips on how to use the mentioned workaround when working with Textpattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a new directory for your Textpattern project, let&amp;#8217;s call it &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;my_blog&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. Then inside the &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;my_blog&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; directory, create three subdirectories: &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;forms&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;pages&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; and finally &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;public&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should now have something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;my_blog
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;forms&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;pages&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;public&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could call the &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;public&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; directory whatever you like, but i&amp;#8217;ll call it &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;public&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. The idea is to keep the files which&amp;#8217;ll live inside &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;forms&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;pages&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; outside of the root directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go get a fresh copy of Textpattern (4.3.0), and run the setup. When everything is setup and customized to your liking, we&amp;#8217;re ready to setup Textpattern to use &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is, whenever you&amp;#8217;re creating a new page or form in Textpattern, you&amp;#8217;ll want that page or form to point to a &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt;-file which contain all of the Texpattern tags &lt;br /&gt;
you&amp;#8217;ll be using, instead of pasting all your code into pages or forms. You&amp;#8217;ll still be pasting a lot, but instead it is a short snippet that points to the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt;-file Textpattern will use instead. Here is what that snippet looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;txp:php&amp;gt;echo parse(file_get_contents(txpath.'/../../directory/file.php'));&amp;lt;/txp:php&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directory is either &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;pages&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;forms&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;, you could even go ahead and create subdirectories within &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;forms&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; for the different form types (&amp;#8220;section&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;link&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;article&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;misc&amp;#8221; etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now you&amp;#8217;ll spend most of your time working within your text-editor, which is much more convenient. When the time comes to show of your project to the world, keep in mind that &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;pages&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;forms&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; will live &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the root of your server. There are probably other and better ways to do this, but this is how i do it at the moment, and it works pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Version Six</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/version-six"/>
   <updated>2010-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/version-six</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Woah…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was nearly two years ago since the last redesign, this marks the sixth version of &lt;em&gt;carlrafting.com&lt;/em&gt;, which i registered almost five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The path to get here hasn’t been that straightforward, i believe any designer can agree that redesigning your own personal website is one of the hardest thing to pull off, but now it’s here, and i’ve learned some stuff along the way which i thought i’d like to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost track on how many iterations i’ve gone through before getting here, but i guess it’s something close to 20… Yeah crazy. As you can see the color palette is very similar to what i’ve had before, it’s just a matter of tweaking it a bit. This design is actually an evolution of an earlier idea i had, which started in Photoshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;OOCSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t say i fully grasp the idea behind &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;OOCSS&lt;/span&gt;, but the stuff that managed to stick to my brain, i’ve tried to incorporate during the development, and i must say i really like the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before, i used to write my &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; in a more location dependent manner, this time it’s pretty much the opposite. The problem with location dependent &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;, to me, is that i find it harder to scan the document and also, i find it pretty hard to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what i refer to as location dependent css:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;p {
	margin: 0 0 20px;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#css {
	margin: 0;
	background: red;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#css p {
	margin: 0 0 40px;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this bit of code assumes that the &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; element should be contained within &lt;code&gt;#css&lt;/code&gt;. I’ve seen a lot of people writing &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; like this, and still do, and it used to be the way i prefered to write &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you imagine for a second that there are more elements that should have other styles than their default, within &lt;code&gt;#css&lt;/code&gt;. Since one read left-to-right the first thing you’ll read is &lt;code&gt;#css&lt;/code&gt;, and this bothered me alot, it&amp;#8217;s hard to read and it also has an impact on performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theres one downside to location independent &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; as i see it, compared to &amp;#8220;regular&amp;#8221; location dependent. It’s that the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; will contain more classes, but to me the benefits outweighs that. Writing location independent &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; gives more control of the styling and makes it easier to maintain and scan the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what i refer to as location independent &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;p {
	margin: 0 0 20px;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.css {
	bakground: red;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.css-blurb {
	margin: 0 0 40px;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this case the &lt;code&gt;.css-blurb&lt;/code&gt; is applied directly to the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element in the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;. I still do have some location dependency in my &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; but it’s not as common as it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; &amp;amp; HTMLFormatting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve gone with another approach regarding formatting of the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTNL&lt;/span&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&quot;text&quot;&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Curabitur at purus vel justo elementum convallis facilisis quis leo. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Phasellus fringilla urna vel ipsum varius gravida id eu tortor.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;body {
	font-family: Helvetica;
	font-size: 13px;
	font-style: normal;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&quot;text&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Curabitur at purus vel justo elementum convallis facilisis quis leo. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Phasellus fringilla urna vel ipsum varius gravida id eu tortor.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;body {
font-family: Helvetica;
font-size: 13px;
font-style: normal;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why this? Well in this case it’s a matter of readability, i just find the second example a lot more natural to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with nicely formatted &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; isn&amp;#8217;t the formatting itself, it&amp;#8217;s that when implementing it with a &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;, it&amp;#8217;ll in most cases mangle it and it wont be as pretty anymore, so i&amp;#8217;ve gone with another approach when writing &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working With Ems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing i incoroporated was to more rely on ems instead of pixels, now i still use pixels for widths and font-size, dealing with ems and font-size inheritance is a major headache i could do without.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could probably go with ems on @widht@s and @padding@s as well, but i discovered this quite late in the process and incorporating this with the typography was easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve read a lot about ems in the past so it wasn&amp;#8217;t completely new to me, but to acctually use it in a project like this made me see the beauty of it, it&amp;#8217;s just a matter of changing the &lt;code&gt;font-size&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;margin&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;line-height&lt;/code&gt; will adjust based on &lt;code&gt;font-size&lt;/code&gt;, beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also done things a bit differently with my &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt; of choice, Textpattern, but i’ll save that for an upcoming article, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>24 ways: Optimize Your Web Design Workflow</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/24-ways-optimize-your-web-design-workflow"/>
   <updated>2010-12-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/24-ways-optimize-your-web-design-workflow</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I fully agree with Veerle, that it&amp;#8217;s necessary to use photoshop to able to achieve maximum creative freedom. It&amp;#8217;s something about working with markup and style that not always enable one to be fully creative… I should also mention that i really enjoy these kind of practical articles, they&amp;#8217;re really valuable in that you get the chance to see how other designers workflow looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then i also believe that it&amp;#8217;s easy to set the wrong expectations for clients, if you show them static comps, because these days there are more ways we can accomplish certain effects in &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;, and if we as web designers really want to take full advantage of the latest &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; technologies, then the best way is probably to show them &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So i do believe a way to combine these workflows will benefit the project a lot.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Learning Git</title>
   <link href="http://carlrafting.com/learning-git"/>
   <updated>2010-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://carlrafting.com/learning-git</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ve probably heard about this version control system called &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike Subversion, you write commands in the command line, in Terminal on Mac for example. For a designer who spend his day in Photoshop or a text-editor, the command line can be quite daunting. Over the past year or so, i&amp;#8217;ve been learning a bit about how to work with the command line, so i&amp;#8217;ve build up quite a tolerance towards working with it, but i don&amp;#8217;t think it&amp;#8217;s necessary to know anything about how a command line works in order to learn the basics of Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out the whole process of working  with Git is quite straightforward, combine Git with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and there&amp;#8217;s no reason not to learn it. I would even say it&amp;#8217;s quicker and easier than to work with a Subversion &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;http://versionsapp.com/&quot;&gt;Versions&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zennaware.com/cornerstone/index.php&quot;&gt;Cornerstone&lt;/a&gt;. I used to work with Versions (Subversion) at my former workplace, and there was almost always problems with it, out of date, conflicts, you name it. Of course you could prevent these problems by making sure everything is in order, but you don&amp;#8217;t wan&amp;#8217;t to spend time organizing and managing files, right? So Git seems a lot more friction-free in this matter, i haven&amp;#8217;t used it for collaboration yet but the whole idea that you add and commit on your local machine, seems to take away most of the problems you have to deal with something like Subversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s some helpful links to get started with Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;Git &amp;#8211; Fast Version Control System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alistapart.com/articles/get-started-with-git/&quot;&gt;Get Started with Git&lt;/a&gt; I really recommend you read this first, it will cover the basics.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://video.linuxfoundation.org/video/1516&quot;&gt;Git in one hour&lt;/a&gt; Pretty good, but a bit hard to keep up with.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gitref.org/&quot;&gt;Git Reference&lt;/a&gt; A good reference if you get stuck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be discouraged if you don’t understand everything right away, i certainly don’t, just try to get the basics right and that should work for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
